Carolyn G. Heilbrun Papers, 1846-1979
Mortimer Rare Book Room
Carolyn G. Heilbrun Papers
1846-1979
Heilbrun, Carolyn G., 1926-
MS 11 UUID:27569c59-64e0-4225-acde-0c560411a0d6
3 boxes (1.25 linear ft.)
Mortimer Rare Book Room Smith College Northampton, MA
Professor and decorated writer who wrote The Garnett Family (1961) and Christopher Isherwood (1971). Includes correspondence, newspaper articles, photographs of the Garnett family, notes, and interviews relating to the two aforementioned works.
Biographical Note
CAROLYN G. HEILBRUN, 1926-2003
In 1993, Carolyn Heilbrun became Avalon Foundation Professor in the Humanities Emerita at Columbia University, after thirty-three years of teaching there. She had fellowships from the Guggenheim and Rockefeller Foundations, and from the NEH. In 1984, she was President of the Modern Language Association. She was a visiting professor at Princeton, Swarthmore, Yale, Union Theological Seminary, the University of California, and at Columbia and Yale Law schools and has received many honorary degrees from colleges and universities. She received the Lifetime Achievement Award from the Modern Language Association in 2000, and was elected to the American Academy of Arts and Sciences in 2000. Heilbrun published: The Garnett Family, Christopher Isherwood, Toward a Recognition of Androgyny, Reinventing Womanhood, Writing a Woman's Life, Hamlet's Mother and Other Women, The Education of A Woman: A Life of Gloria Steinem, The Last Gift of Time, and the University of Toronto Alexander Lectures, Women's Lives: The View from the Threshold, and When All Our Models Were Men: My Teachers Barzun, Fadiman, Trilling. She published numerous articles and reviews. Under the name Amanda Cross, she published fourteen mystery novels. Heilbrun died on October 9, 2003.
RICHARD GARNETT, 1835-1906
Richard Garnett was an English librarian and writer. He served on the staff of the British Museum (1851-1899) as keeper of printed books (1890-1899); and director (from 1880). In 1905 Garnett published a general catalogue of the British Museum. He also wrote Relics of Shelley (1862), The Twilight of the Gods (1888, fables), History of Italian Literature (1897), and several biographies. Richard Garnett was the father of Edward Garnett.
CONSTANCE (BLACK) GARNETT, 1862-1946
Constance Garnett was the wife of Edward Garnett and mother of David Garnett. Her translations of many Russian writers, such as Dostoevsky, achieved great popularity in the first two decades of the twentieth century and had a profound influence on modernist writers. Garnett studied classics at Newnham College, Cambridge University, and began to learn Russian in the early 1890s.
EDWARD GARNETT, 1868-1937
Edward Garnett was the father of David Garnett, husband of Constance Garnett, and son of Richard Garnett. As a publisher's reader and critic, he discovered, advised, and tutored many British writers, including Conrad, Galsworthy, Ford Maddox Ford, D.H. Lawrence, and W.H. Hudson. Garnett also authored plays, including The Breaking Point (1907), The Feud (1907), and The Trial of Jeanne d'Arc (1912).
DAVID GARNETT, 1892-1981
David Garnett was the only child of Edward and Constance Garnett, and was known almost universally as "Bunny." Although trained at the Royal College of Science as a botanist, he later turned to a highly successful literary career. Among his twenty-one works of fiction, Lady into Fox (1922) is notable for having won both the Hawthornden and Tait-Black prizes for 1923. The unexpected success of this novel led Bunny to withdraw in 1924 from the bookshop he had established in 1920 with Francis Birell to devote more time to his writing. From 1923 to 1935 he was partner in the Nonesuch Press, and from 1932 to 1935 he was literary editor of the New Statesman and Nation. He wrote several memoirs.
CHRISTOPHER ISHERWOOD, 1904-1986
Christopher Isherwood was an American-English novelist, poet and playwright. He authored autobiographical and quasi-autobiographical works including the short-story collection Goodbye to Berlin (1939), the novels: The World in the Evening (1954), Down There On A Visit (1962), A Meeting by the River (1967), and Christopher and His Kind (1976). His work included screenwriting for various film studios (from 1939). As a convert, Isherwood wrote, edited, and translated works on Vedantism.
Sources:
Hussey, Mark. Virginia Woolf A to Z. New York, 1995.
Merriam-Webster's Biographical Dictionary. Merriam-Webster Incorporated, 1995.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Carolyn G. Heilbrun Papers consist of 1.25 linear feet of material, dating from 1846 to 1979, relating to her works: The Garnett Family (1961) and Christopher Isherwood (1971). Types of materials include correspondence, newspaper articles, photographs of the Garnett family, notes, and interviews. This collection was donated to Smith College by Carolyn Heilbrun in November 1989. The papers are arranged in four series.
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized into four series:
I. Garnett Family, 1846-1960
II. The Garnett Family by Carolyn G. Heilbrun, 1955-1960
III. Christopher Isherwood by Carolyn G. Heilbrun, 1974-1979
IV. Interview with Alice G. Fredman, 1977
Arrangement of the Collection
The papers are arranged in four series.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The Carolyn G. Heilbrun Papers are the physical property of the Mortimer Rare Book Room, Smith College. Literary rights, including copyright, belong to the authors of the works or their legal representatives.
History of the Collection
This collection was donated to Smith College by Carolyn Heilbrun in November 1989.
Search Terms
Heilbrun, Carolyn G., 1926-; Garnett, Richard, 1835-1906.; Garnett, Constance Black, 1862-1946.; Garnett, Edward, 1868-1937.; Garnett, David, 1892-; Isherwood, Christopher, 1904-; Fredman, Alice Green, 1924-; Garnett family.; Isherwood, Christopher, 1904-; Forster, E. M. (Edward Morgan), 1879-1970.; Fredman, Alice Green, 1924-; Spender, Stephen, 1909-
- Series I. Garnett Family, 1846-1960, .5 linear ft. (51 items)
  This series is organized into four subseries: Correspondence, Memoirs, Newspaper Articles, and Photographs.
  Correspondence (transcriptions)
  This subseries includes correspondence of the Garnett family. Most extensive is the correspondence of Edward Garnett with authors such as Joseph Conrad (Box 1, folder 6) and D.H. Lawrence (Box 1, folders 9-10). Also included is the correspondence of Richard Garnett (Box 1, folders 3-4) and members of the Patten and Black families (Box 1, folders 1-2). All of the letters are transcriptions. This series does not include original correspondence.
  Memoirs
  This subseries contains memoirs by members of the Garnett family. Olivia Rayne Garnett recounts the early life of her parents, Richard Garnett and Olivia Narney Garnett (Box 1, folder 13). Constance Garnett writes of the Garnett and Black families (Box 1, folder 11), and David Garnett's "Constance Garnett" contains memories of his mother (Box 1, folder 12).
  Newspaper Articles
  This subseries includes newspaper articles about members of the Garnett family. These consist of book reviews, obituaries, and related articles. The bulk of the articles are original clippings from the 1950s, along with transcriptions of earlier articles.
  Photographs
  This subseries includes black and white prints of members of the Garnett family. It contains photographs of Richard Garnett, his wife Olivia Narney Garnett, and their children. Also included are photographs of Constance (Black) Garnett, Edward Garnett, and David Garnett.
- Series II. The Garnett Family by Carolyn Heilbrun, 1955-1960, .25 linear ft. (25 items)
  This series is organized into four subseries: Correspondence, Notes, Evaluations and Corrections, and Publication Materials.
  Includes material related to The Garnett Family, Heilbrun's dissertation at Columbia University, which was published in 1961.
  Correspondence
  This subseries includes the correspondence of Carolyn G. Heilbrun concerning The Garnett Family. Many of the letters seek permission to quote correspondence with Edward Garnett. Correspondents include E.M. Forster (Box 2, folder 36), Stephen Spender (Box 2, folder 45), and various publishers. Particularly extensive is correspondence with B. W. Huebesch of the Viking Press (Box 2, folder 41).
  Notes
  This subseries includes Carolyn Heilbrun's notes for The Garnett Family. Particularly extensive are her notes on Richard, Constance, and Edward Garnett.
  Evaluations and Corrections
  This subseries includes corrections and evaluations of The Garnett Family by members of the Columbia University faculty.
  Publication Materials
  This series includes a copyright application for The Garnett Family. It also includes a summary of The Garnett Family for the microfilm publication of the thesis.
- Series III. Christopher Isherwood by Carolyn Heilbrun, 1974-1979, .5 linear ft. (10 items)
  This series includes interviews of and about Christopher Isherwood. All are audio recordings. There are transcriptions of the interviews conducted by Heilbrun and of Isherwood's Modern Languages Association Address, as well as television and radio interviews.
  Excerpts from three of the interviews conducted by Heilbrun were published in Twentieth Century Literature Volume 22 (October 1976).
- Series IV. Interview with Alice G. Fredman, 1977, (1 item)
  The audiotape in this series records an interview with Alice G. Fredman, writer and professor. This interview was conducted by Carolyn Heilbrun. It is one of a series of interviews about women who had careers before the Women's Liberation movement, especially the generation born in the 1920s.
- Series I. Garnett Family, 1846-1960
  - Correspondence of the Garnetts, (transcriptions)
    - DAVID BLACK
      - Patten, Clara (from) [1846] Aug 17-1846 Aug 27 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Patten, [George] (to) 1846 Aug 18 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - RICHARD GARNETT
      - Butler, Samuel (from) 1893 Dec 10 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Hardy, Thomas (from) 1904 Dec 9 (Box 1)
      - Woodbury, G.E. (from) 1890 Feb 3 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - EDWARD AND CONSTANCE GARNETT
      - Conrad, Joseph (to) 1896 Mar 26-1923 Dec 5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Forster, E. M. (from) 1907 Sep 7 [or Aug 9?] (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Huebesch, B.W. (to) 1902 Jun 10 -1931 Jul 7 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Lawrence, D.H. and Frieda (from) 1911 Sep 10-1921 Nov 10, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Memoirs
    Arranged alphabetically by author.
    - Garnett, Constance. Memoir about the Black and Garnett families: typescript transcription n.d., 118 pages. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Garnett, David. "Constance Garnett": typescript n.d., 6 pages. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Garnett, Olivia Rayne. Memoir about the early life of her parents, Richard and Olivia Narney Garnett: typescript n.d., 6 pages, (2 copies). (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper Articles
    Arranged by subject.
    - RICHARD GARNETT (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Symons, Arthur. "Richard Garnett." The Speaker 1906 Apr 21., typescript transcription (2 copies)
    - CONSTANCE GARNETT (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - "Interpreting Tolstoy." Times Literary Supplement 1954 Jul 16, pages 449-50.
      - "New Translations" review of David Magarshack's translation of Fyodor Dostoevsky's The Devils. Times Literary Supplement 1954 Apr 30
      - Review of Jessie Coulson's translation of Crime and Punishment. Times Literary Supplement 1954 Jan 22
      - "Unerring Nose for Humbug of Any Sort." The New York Times Book Review 1955
    - EDWARD GARNETT (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Green, Henry. "Edward Garnett" The New Statesman and Nation 1950 Dec 30, page 675.
      - Miles, Hamish. "Edward Garnett." The New Statesman and Nation 1937 Feb 27, page 327. (2 copies)
      - Moore, Harry T. "Hand-Up for an Author" Review of Joseph Conrad: Letters to William Blackwood and David S. Meldrum. The New York Times Book Review 1958 Nov 30, page 62.
      - Murray, J. Middleton. Review of Edward Garnett's Collected Essays. The Nation and Athenaeum 1922 Jul 22, pages 568-9.
      - Pritchett, V. S. "London Letter." The New York Times Rook Review 1958 Jan 21, page 22.
      - Scott-James. R. A. "Edward Garnett" The Spectator 1937 Feb 26, page 362.
    - DAVID GARNETT (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - "Books: Two Freedoms." Review of Aspects of Love 1956 Jan 28, page 95.
      - Davenport, John. "New Novels: Symbols and Sentiments." Review of A Shot in the Dark by David Garnett. The Observer 1958 Nov 2, page 22.
      - "Escape to the Sun." Review of A Shot in the Dark by David Garnett. The Times Literary Supplement 1958 Nov 21
      - Fearing, Kenneth, "Love Without Tears." Review of Aspects of Love. The New York Times Book Review 1956 Feb 5, page 4.
      - Hutchens, John K. Book review Aspects of Love by David Garnett. The New York Herald Tribune 1956 Jan 27, page 15.
      - "Neo-Pagan." Review of Aspects of Love by David Garnett. Time 1956 Jan 30
      - Nicolson, Harold. "Self-portrait in Profile" Review of The Flowers of the Forest by David Garnett. The Observer 1955 Oct 9
      - Peterson, Virgilia. "Growing Up in Bloomsbury." Review of The Flowers of the Forest by David Garnett. Saturday Review 1956 Sept 8, page 43.
      - Pippett, Aileen. "Memory is a Golden Thing." Review of The Flowers of the Forest, Vol. 2 of The Golden Echo by David Garnett. The New York Times Book Review 1956 Sept 2, page 6.
      - Poore, Charles "Books of the Times." Review of Aspects of Love by David Garnett. The New York Times 1956 Jan 26
      - Rosselli, John. "Was T.E. Lawrence a Fake?" The Reporter 1955 Apr 21, pages 49-52.
      - West, Anthony. "Books: Through a Glass, Darkly." The New Yorker 1960 May 28, pages 137-142.
  - Photographs, (black and white prints)
    Arranged alphabetically by subject.
    - Garnett, Constance by David Garnett n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Bloomsbury Iconography B2
    - Garnett, Constance by David Garnett 1942 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Garnett, Constance n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Garnett, Constance in group photograph n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Garnett, Constance with Katherine and Grace Black n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Garnett, David "aged 12" (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Garnett, David n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Bloomsbury Iconography A20
    - Garnett, David (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Garnett, Edward as a child n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Garnett, Edward n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Bloomsbury Iconography A1
    - Garnett, Edward 1917 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Garnett, Olivia Narney 1866 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Garnett, Olivia Narney by Frederick Hollyer 1899 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Garnett, Richard with book n.d. (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Garnett, Richard with book, profile n.d. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Garnett family, includes Olivia Narney Garnett ("Mrs. Richard Garnett") with May, Robert, Edward, Olive, Lucy, and Arthur Garnett and Christiana Chapple, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 32)
      With envelopes addressed to Heilbrun from David Garnett
- Series II. The Garnett Family by Carolyn Heilbrun, 1955-1960
  - Correspondence of Carolyn Heilbrun regarding The Garnett Family
    Arranged alphabetically.
    - Alfred A. Knopf, Inc 1958 Sep 8- 1958 Sep 26 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Chatto & Windus Ltd with letter of introduction from B. W. Huebesch 1955 Nov 21 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Forster, E.M. 1958 Dec 2-1959 Jan 1 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Frost, Robert
      See: Box 2, folder 39 and 43
    - Gerald Duckworth & Co. 1955 Nov 21 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Harcourt, Brace & Company 1955 Aug 29 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Henry Holt and Company 1958 Dec 2-1960 Mar 29 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Huebesch, B. W. 1955 Nov 2-1960 Mar 1 (Box 2, Folder 39)
      See also: Box 2, folder 35
    - J. M. Dent & Sons 1959 Feb 3-1960 Mar 3 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Jonathan Cape (Firm) 1955 Nov 21- 1959 Feb 11 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Lawrence Pollinger Limited 29 Jan 1959-1960 Mar 29 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Spender, Stephen 1958 Dec 2-1959 Jan 1 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Viking Press
      See: Box 2, folder 40
    - Unidentified 1953 Dec 13, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Notes for The Garnett Family
    - General (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Richard Garnett (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Edward and Constance Garnett (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - David Garnett (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Research Notebooks (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Evaluations and corrections (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Hazen: holograph n.d., 4 leaves. (Box 2)
    - Shearer, James F.: typescript, n.d. 1 page, with paper scrap 1959 Apr 28. (Box 2)
    - Suther: typescript n.d., 2 pages. (Box 2)
    - Unidentified: typescript n.d., 2 pages. (Box 2)
  - Publication materials
    Arranged chronologically.
    - Certificate of copyright registration 1960 Feb 24 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Summary for the microfilm publication of The Garnett Family (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Series III. Christopher Isherwood by Carolyn Heilbrun, 1974-1979
  - Interviews, (audio tapes and transcriptions)
    - Isherwood, Christopher. Interview by James Day on Day at Night, Broadcast 1974 Jun 2, Audiotape #3. (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Isherwood, Christopher. Address to the Modern Language Association: typescript 1974 Dec, 49 pages, with audiotapes #1 and 2 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Isherwood, Christopher. Interview by Carolyn Heilbrun: typescript A 1975 Jul 25, 71 pages. (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Isherwood, Christopher. Interview by Carolyn Heilbrun: typescript B, corrected 1975 Jul 25, 28 pages. (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Isherwood, Christopher. Interview by Carolyn Heilbrun: typescript C 1975 Jul 25, 24 pages, with audiotapes #4 and 5. (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Isherwood, Christopher. Interview by Carolyn Heilbrun: typescript 1975 28 Jul, 38 pages, with audiotape #6. (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Lambert, Gavin interview by Carolyn Heilbrun: typescript A 1975 Jul 28, 29 pages. (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Lambert, Gavin interview by Carolyn Heilbrun: typescript B with introduction 1975 Jul 28, 21 pages, with audiotape #7. (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Isherwood, Christopher. Interview by Carolyn Heilbrun: 1976 May 23, 58 pages, with audiotape #8. (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Isherwood, Christopher on The Dick Cavett Show 1979, Audiotape #10. (Box 3, Folder 62)
- Series IV. Interview with Alice G. Fredman, 1977
  - Fredman, Alice G. Interview by Carolyn Heilbrun 1977 Nov 30., Audiotape #9. (Box 3, Folder 63)